Let me show you a tweet.
>> Former hobbits, if you have ever
considered returning to Palunteer, this
is the week to do it. The world is
demanding every last unit of creative
energy we can muster. From the foxhole
to the factory floor, the surface area
to support something incredibly
meaningful immediately is immense. If
you have been chasing that spark, come
find it again. The Shire is calling.
This is a tweet. Sorry, ex post from Ted
Mabry, global head of commercial at
Palanteer, which is a real Vincent adult
man job title if ever I heard one. It
was posted back in March 2026, just days
after the US and Israel began conducting
strikes on Iran. Palanteer, the company
that Mabberry works for, was riding high
and its executives were desperate to
tell everyone of the crucial role that
Palanteer's software had played in
identifying targets for the strikes.
Obviously current current operations are
ongoing but I think people will reflect
back and say this is the the first large
scale combat operation that was um
really uh driven enhanced made
substantially more productive with
technology with AI.
>> This excitement would later call when it
was reported that Palanteer's Maven
smart system had been involved in
choosing to bomb a primary school in
Manab killing at least 168 mostly
children. If an AR system recommends a
target that later turns out to involve
civilians, where does responsibility for
that lie?
>> That is with the military organization.
And yet, while America's strikes on Iran
were losing Donald Trump support both
domestically and on the international
stage, Palanteers employees were clearly
excited about this new opportunity to
fulfill their company's founding mission
of defending the West. We have dedicated
our company to the service of the West
and the United States of America, and
we're super proud of the role we play,
especially in places we can't talk
about. Mabber's tweet, however, wasn't
just notable for its enthusiasm. It
captured so much of the weirdness of
Palunteer, the cultural appropriation of
computer nerds talking about foxholds,
the obsession with grand narratives of
good and evil, the deeply cringe
references to Lord of the Rings. I don't
know why.
It makes me sad.
>> Over the past few years, this weirdness
has allowed Palunteer to develop a kind
of mystique. It's quickly become one of
the world's most controversial
organizations, beloved by some, hated by
others. Vanishingly few people are on
the fence. If you're watching this
video, you probably know something about
Palanteer. Maybe you know they work with
Data. Maybe you know they're connected
to Peter Teal. Maybe you know they have
military contracts, but also health
ones. You've probably at least picked up
on the fact that they're named after the
weird walkie-talkie stone from Lord of
the Rings.
>> Palanteer and the hobbits which work for
it revel in the intrigue which surrounds
its work, which is a problem because
this esoteric company increasingly has
the ear of governments across the world,
including here in the UK. In today's
video, we're going to try and break down
exactly what Palanteer is, where it came
from, and what it does. And in order to
do so, I'm going to introduce you to
three people, three technologies, and
three political ideas which can decode
this company. So, to Mount Doom we go.
We already sort of have
two towers
kind of.
>> Let me show you a video.
>> You would prefer the human race to
endure, right?
>> Uh,
>> you're hesitating. Well, I
>> Yes.
>> I don't know. I I would
>> I would um
>> This is a long hesitation. So many long
hesitation.
>> There's so many questions and questions.
>> Should the human race survive?
>> Uh yes. But this is Peter T, co-founder
and chairman of Palunteer.
>> If you hang out in the same corners of
the internet I do, you might have seen
clips from this interview during the
round already. Maybe you persevered
through it all. Teal is being
interviewed by Ross Duther, the foremost
conservative columnist at the New York
Times, and the conversation only gets
weirder. Tal will go on to suggest that
Greta Tunberg might be the antichrist.
We need to stop science. We need to just
say stop to this. And this is where
Yeah, I don't know. In the 17th century,
I can imagine a doctor strange love,
Edward Teller type person taking over
the world. In our world, it's far more
likely to be Greta Thunberg.
>> It would be easy to assume that Peter
Teal's hatred for Greta and humanity is
part of the same sudden rightward shift
which a lot of tech CEOs and
self-described founders have been making
lately.
>> Seeing Donald Trump get up after getting
shot in the face and pump his fist in
the air with the American flag is one of
the most badass things I've ever seen in
my life. But Peter Teal has been a
right-wing weirdo since day do. And
look, maybe this wasn't all his fault.
Born in Frankfurt in Germany, Teal spent
several years of his childhood living in
South Africa and what is now Namibia,
both of which were then under apartheid.
And if that sounds bad enough, the town
that Teal's family lived in was home to
a sizable community of German expats
who, and I'm not making this up here,
were known for their admiration of the
Third Reich. As recently as the mid1
1970s, a reporter from the New York
Times reported that residents would
regularly greet each other with shouts
of hile Hitler. So yeah, we can say
maybe his parents didn't give him the
best start. And yet the apple certainly
didn't fall particularly far from the
tree. When he arrived to study
philosophy at Stamford University in the
1980s, he was quick to join the campus
culture wars. This was a period in which
despite having their boy Ronald Reagan
in the White House, the right was
continuing to lose ground on the
cultural front. The eyes of the nation
were on Stanford in 1987 when it opted
to abolish a compulsory humanities
course known as Western Civ, a kind of
great books module centered on 15 core
texts. Students had grown increasingly
critical of the reading list's
whiteness, its euroentrism, and lack of
female authors. Teal, then in his
sophomore year, responded to the
abolition of the module by launching the
Stanford Review, a campus newspaper
dedicated to publishing quote unquote
alternative views. This, of course, just
meant contrarian conservative ideas. One
issue published during his tenure as
editor-inchief includes an article
accusing gay students of trying to
incite homophobic incidents to garner
sympathy, a proposal for an onampus
house for conservatives, which it
describes as the smallest and most
oppressed minority on campus, and
another think piece which just really,
really, really hates bicycles. All of
this might sound a little bit tangential
to Palanteer, but the Stanford Review
was in some ways the fire in which
Palanteer was forged. A journalist at
Stanford Politics, a modern-day rival
campus publication, identified 24 people
who had written for or been associated
with the Stanford Review, who later
wound up working for Palanteer. But how
did a philosophy grad wind up founding
what is regarded by some at least as a
boundary pushing tech company? Well,
partly by being a rich kid and partly by
getting pretty lucky in the dotcom boom.
Teal was one of three co-founders of
PayPal, which was initially intended to
be so much more than it is today. In
keeping with Teal's right-wing
worldview, the original plan had been to
create a digital currency which might
replace the US dollar, thereby
liberating the world from central banks.
It was effectively Bitcoin before
Bitcoin was Bitcoin. PayPal today is
obviously not that. Unlike Bitcoin,
PayPal is decidedly legitimate and the
technology which helped it become
legitimate is the seed from which
Palanteer grew.
It didn't take long for PayPal to run
into trouble. In some ways, it was a
victim of its own success. So easy was
it to sign up, to send, or receive money
that it became incredibly popular among
fraudsters and money launderers. None of
this was helped by the fact that PayPal
had tried to woo new customers by
offering $10 to anyone who signed up.
And that's in 1999 money. That would be
$19.99
today
just for signing up. If you could work
out how to automate the opening of new
accounts, then it wasn't too hard to
make serious money. Very quickly, the
company was losing $10 million to
fraudulent transactions and sign on
bonuses every single month. This not
only affected customer relations, but
caused banks and card processing
companies to view the platform with
suspicion. For a payment provider, all
of this was terminal. One guy who didn't
care too much about all of this was Elon
Musk, whose ex.com, the first one, not
the second one, had merged with Teal's
company, in a deal which also made Musk
CEO. Teal and his co-founder, Max
Levchin, were terrified that Musk's lack
approach to fraud could sink the
company. While Musk was away on his
honeymoon, then they thus launched a
coup, firing Musk and installing Teal as
CEO in his place. As a former
cryptography guy, this was a task that
Levchin could have been made for. His
first solution was to develop what we
now know as the capture. Using captures
to verify that anyone signing up for a
PayPal account was a human being
instantly wiped out the possibility of
using bots to set up multiple fake
accounts. The spark which lit the flame
of Palanteer, however, was a piece of
software known as Eigor. Igor was named
for a Russian fraudster who had become a
real thorn in PayPal's side. His scam of
choice was to open a bunch of eBay
accounts and then create sales listings
for products which didn't exist. Using a
separate account, he would then buy the
fake products using stolen credit cards
and choose for those payments to be
processed through PayPal. He would then
withdraw the money from the seller's
PayPal account before using the buyer's
account to complain that the product
hadn't been delivered. Because PayPal
guaranteed all transactions, the result
was that he got to walk away with
PayPal's money. Levchin and his new
anti-fraud team, however, noticed that
there were patterns to Igor's scam
sales. He would be accessing the site
from certain IP addresses or using cards
which hadn't been used on PayPal before.
Maybe he was listing and making sales at
certain times. Eigor, the software, not
the hacker, was designed to look out for
these patterns of behavior, which might
imply that a transaction could be
fraudulent. What made it particularly
revolutionary at the time, was that it
took into account multiple data points.
Previous similar systems might only have
taken into account a single factor. What
time a transaction was completed or the
format of an email address for instance,
which made it fairly simple for a
fraudster to circumn these systems by
just completing their transactions at
different times by looking at hundreds
of data points at once. Eigor was far
harder to get past. PayPal system also
used machine learning. The software was
constantly looking at historic
transaction data to find new ways of
recognizing probable scammers. Tech
reporters at the time loved comparing
Eigor to the precogs in Minority Report,
which was then a super recent film. It
was, they suggested, a form of
predictive policing for online fraud. It
could sus out who was likely to be a
scammer before they'd even started their
scam. The software even boasted a slick
user interface through which it would
present Levchin's 100 strong anti-fraud
team. its findings. Pretty soon, the
PayPal team had completed their goal. By
2001, fraud accounted for just 0.45%
of transactions, down from 0.85% in
2000. This ensured they were now getting
attention for all the right reasons. The
FBI soon became regular visitors to the
PayPal offices, keen to use the Eagle
platform to confirm fraud reports. Of
course, something else happened in 2001
which would make TL and Co's new
predictive policing powers even more
valuable to the government than Eagle
had been to the FBI. On the morning of
the 11th of September 2001, members of
the terrorist group Alqaaida hijacked
four commercial airplanes and managed to
fly two into the Twin Towers of the
World Trade Center and one into the
Pentagon, with another being downed by
passengers in a field in Pennsylvania.
What was somewhat awkward for the
authorities after the event was that
America's security services had had all
the scraps of information which could
have told them that these attacks were
going to take place. It was simply that
those scraps were all held by different
teams in different agencies in different
places and they weren't talking to one
another. The logic emerged that what the
government needed was a system which
could join the dots between such
disperate data points to work out where
an attack might come from next in order
to stop it before it could happen. There
is an extent then to which Peter Teal
happened into founding Palanteer. But
even amid the paranoia and clash of
civilizations patriotism which defined
the war on terror, Teal's way of seeing
the world stood out. We'll come back to
the technology of Palanteer shortly, but
first we need to introduce our first
idea.
It's time to talk about the antichrist.
You're just going to have to accept that
this video is going to go to some pretty
weird places. Okay,
>> I said at the top of this video that we
weren't just going to encounter people
and technologies on this journey, but
also ideals because if there's one thing
which really sets Palunteer apart from
its contemporaries, it's that this is an
intentionally and proudly political
company. In order to understand the deep
sense of paranoia which shapes this
company, you need to understand just a
slither of Peter Teal's beliefs about
the Antichrist. If it is so, there
should not be any human society. It
should be impossible.
>> Con total conflict all the time.
>> Total conflict all the time.
>> This is Renee Gerard, French philosopher
and theologian and perhaps Peter Teal's
biggest intellectual influence. In fact,
most of Teal's current turn as an
antichrist expert is borrowed more or
less directly from Gerard. Central to
Gerard and thus Teal's thinking is
something called mimemetic theory. This
is the idea that human desire isn't
individual but is mimemetic. If you want
something, it's not because you have
individually decided that you want that
thing, but that you have seen that
someone else wants that thing and have
mimicked their desire. Tea said that it
was his enthusiasm for Gerard's mimetic
theory which led him to invest in
Facebook. Facebook view through a
sheradian lens is a tool for discovering
and replicating the desires of others.
It's a medium which actively breeds
trends and memes. The users will be
drawn to such a technology seemed to
teal obvious. This alignment of desires,
however, is problematic. Everyone
wanting the same things inherently leads
to conflict.
There are usually only so many of a
given thing or experience to go around
with the result that everyone just ends
up fighting with one another. This is
true of consumer culture and other
aspects of our personal lives, but it's
also true of geopolitics.
And this is where Teal believes the
antichrist also comes into play. See,
nation states also regularly end up
caught in frenzies of fighting over
technologies and resources which they
sometimes only seem to want because they
want to beat other countries to the
punch. The scramble for Africa, the
nuclear bomb, the space race, today's
anguish over AI and microchips. What
Teal really fears, however, is not
conflict between governments, but the
absence of it. Teal is terrified about
the development of a one world
government. In fact, the more peaceful a
one world government might prove itself
to be, the worse. See, as a good
Christian, Peter Teal knows his Bible.
He's particularly obsessed with the line
in Paul's first epistle to the
Thessalonians, which reads that when
they say there is peace and security,
then sudden destruction will come upon
them as labor pains come upon a pregnant
woman and there will be no escape. He
takes this to mean that too much
international collaboration will be a
precursor to Armageddon.
In fact, Teal believes that any
international body which seeks to hold
back human progress through regulation
might be being guided by the Antichrist.
That's right. Any moves to regulate any
of the industries that Peter Teal is
involved in might not just be
inconvenient for him, they are downright
evil. When Tio suggests that Greta
Tunberg might be the antichrist, then
it's because he fears that addressing
climate change would require some kind
of super national organization to police
carbon emissions, which to teal sounds
pretty antichristy. There is, however,
hope. See, in Paul's second epistle to
the Thessalonians, he references
exceptionally briefly something he calls
the catacon or restrainer.
This is some kind of force or person or
thing which holds back the coming of the
Antichrist and Armageddon. Paul is super
vague about exactly what the Catacon is
and so is Teal. At separate times, Teal
has said that the Catacon is likely to
come from San Francisco because it's a
broadly libertarian city. He said the
Catacon might be JD France. He thinks it
almost certainly will come from America.
What's most important to understand
about Teal's Bible tinged philosophy for
the sake of understanding Palanteer
however is that it is a worldview which
is actively allergic to cooperation and
which views collaboration or the pursuit
of peace as unnatural.
>> I don't think in win lose I think in
domination.
So I don't like this win-lose thing
because it it it kind of presupposes
okay to lose. I like you're and I think
domination is important because the it's
very hard to build like it's very hard
to build a business and one of the real
reasons it's hard is you've got to sit
next to someone who is annoying you
every cell in your body every day and
they may be right.
>> This is Alex Karp, one of Peter Teal's
co-founders of Palunteer and its CEO
from very nearly day one. Alex Karp's
journey to working with Palanteer is not
Peter Teals. Not by a long shot. In
fact, there was a time when Palanteer
was the last place you'd have expected
to find him. As an undergraduate
philosophy student at Havford College in
Pennsylvania, Carb had been a model
student radical. He'd organized against
racism on campus, and when time came to
take his yearbook photo, he would
reportedly wore a keffier. Like Teal,
this was a product of his upbringing.
Carp had grown up in liberal
Philadelphia with a Jewish dad and an
African-American mom. Both were
politically active and their son
accompanied them to left-wing protests
and demonstrations. Karp is also
dyslexic. The result was that he found
himself in a world very much not made
for him and he was keen to both
understand it and change it. After
completing his degree at Havford, Carpin
enrolled at Stanford Law School where he
found himself sharing a room with none
other than Peter Teal. Carp and Teal
then were both philosophy grats. They'd
both decided to follow this up by going
to law school. Both would also find that
they didn't actually care that much
about the law. Teal made a slightly
better stab at it than Karp, but still
quit as a lawyer after just 7 months.
And yet Karp and Teal's rooming
relationship was defined by their very
clear differences, namely politics.
Karp, the Jewish socialist, and Teal,
the hardright evangelical, would argue
and argue and argue. It's hard to
imagine either felt they had much hope
of actually winning the other over. But
perhaps that didn't much matter. Both
are to this day deeply contrarian,
seemingly enjoying the fight as much as
any prospect of victory. If Karp's
socialism and broader commitment to
social justice might seem questionable
given his later associations, it's worth
stressing that after graduating from
Stanford, he uprooted his whole life in
order to pursue his interest in social
theory. Because Alex Karp wasn't just
kind of interested in ideas, he was a
theory guy par excalance. In 1992, Karp
moved to Germany. He did so with the
intention to seek out one scholar in
particular, Jurgen Havas. Habamas was
one of the leading humanity scholars of
the second half of the 20th century.
More importantly, he'd come to
prominence as a second generation member
of the Frankfurt school. For Alex Karp
to have secured a place to study for a
PhD under Habamass would have been to
position himself in the intellectual
family tree of Theodor Dorno and
Maxheimer,
giants of the academy. What happened
next depends on who you believe. If you
ask Alex Karp himself, he'll tell you
that Habamas signed on as his PhD
supervisor and that Karp studied under
him for some time until they had a
falling out.
>> I went over the study with him. I was in
his colloquium and I and I studied with
him. Then we had a falling out and then
I finished my PhD with someone else.
>> But even Karp hasn't been a particularly
consistent narrator here. In an earlier
retelling of this episode of his life,
even he suggested that Habamas had
chosen to break off their adviser adise
relationship because Habamas didn't
think Karp's work was good enough.
Jurgen Habamas died earlier this year.
But when asked, his version of the story
was that his interactions with Karp were
pretty minimal and that he certainly was
never his PhD supervisor. Whoever's
telling the truth, Karp's decade in
Germany did not end in academic success.
It took him 10 years to finish his PhD,
during which time he became jaded by the
whole experience. Ausingly, in an
interview a couple of years ago, Cobb
suggested that he grew to dislike
academics and Habamass in particular
because they weren't builders.
>> I had certain abilities they didn't have
to like be a builder. I wouldn't have
put in these terms cuz I hadn't built
anything, but they did have the right
personality for building,
>> which feels a bit like criticizing them
for not being good at basketball or
something. just just not super relevant
to I think what they wanted to be doing.
Karp drifted for a while. He toyed with
becoming an investor. He worked for a
charity. Eventually, he drifted back to
San Francisco, which is where he
reconnected with Peter Teal. Now, while
he may not have been a very good
academic, Alex Karp is really good at
impressing a certain kind of person.
Maybe not you and me, but the rich and
powerful seem to find his obnoxiousness
and his oddness captivating. Peter deal
first set Karp to work securing clients
for his now defunct investment firm
Clarion Capital. Before long, however,
he squanded Karp over to Palantein. More
than this, Alex Karp was made CEO, which
was frankly a mad choice for the
position. Karp had never led an
organization before. He knew nothing
about intelligence or the military. He
didn't know the first thing about code.
The best part of two decades spent at
university, however, had given Karp an
exceptional ability to [__] which
was about to become desperately
important in trying to sell Palunteer's
new technologies to governments.
The key to understanding Palanteer's
software product is to first understand
that Palanteer is not a data company.
They're really keen that you know this.
When the company published a series of
medium posts called Palunteer explained
in 2020, the very first entry outlined
that quote, "We do not collect, store,
or sell personal data. We don't use
personal data to train proprietary AI or
machine learning models to share or
resell to other customers. We never
facilitate the movement of data between
clients except where those specific
clients have entered into an agreement
with each other." Palanteer was born out
of 9/11. Monkey criticism of the US
intelligence services in the aftermath
of those attacks have been that the FBI
and CIA probably did have all the
information necessary to predict and
stop them. That information was simply
too scattered across different offices
and agents. The official 9/11 commission
set up to review the attacks concluded
that the government needed to quote
bring the major national security
institutions into the information
revolution. Palant software then doesn't
itself gather data. It's instead a suite
of tools intended to allow government
organizations and companies better
access to the data that they already
have, particularly in cases where that
information might presently be quite
fragmented. Their key intelligence and
military offering is Palanteer Gotham.
And it looks, as the name would suggest,
a bit like the bat computer. Depending
on one's needs in any given moment, it
can generate maps, timelines, org
charts, it can bring up photos,
satellite imagery, and troop positions.
It could not look more like a video game
if it tried. This probably didn't hurt
when way back in 2004, Alex Karp went to
pitch Palanteer to an organization
called Inutel. Initutel is a venture
capital firm which was set up by the CIA
with the sole purpose of investing in
startups which produce intelligence
software. The idea is that by helping
those companies get off the ground, they
can ensure there is a better range of
cuttingedge technology out there which
the CIA and other American agencies
might be able to buy. Inutel's CEO at
the time was Gilman Louie, an ex video
game designer who had made his name with
a series of hyperrealistic flight sims
called Falcon. According to journalist
Michael Steinberger, when Louie saw a
demo of what was to become Palanteer
Gotham, he quipped that if the new
company didn't work out, Carpon Co.
could always take up video game design
instead. They didn't need to because
Incitel chose to invest in Palanteer to
the tune of $1.25 million. As important
as the cash, however, was the access
that this gave the company. Louisie was
able to arrange for Palanteer staff to
go and work alongside CIA agents to
ensure the software that they were
developing was as useful for them as it
could be. The result 3 years later was
Palente Gotham, a piece of software
which like Eagle before it had the
ability to process a whole range of data
points to give analysts an easy to
understand overview of all the
information the CIA possessed about a
given person, place, or event at any
given time. This period of development
didn't just lead to Palanteer having a
finished piece of software. They'd also
managed to impress the right people at
the CIA enough that they walked away
with their first contract already in
hand. Soon events would conspire again
to allow them to transform that one
contract into many, many more.
>> Tonight, I can report to the American
people and to the world that the United
States has conducted an operation that
killed Osama bin Laden, the leader of
al-Qaeda. On the 2nd of May 2011, Barack
Obama held his most famous press
conference. Before long, rumor began to
spread that Palanteer's software had
been used to locate the man who had
ordered 9/11. It's unclear whether or
not this was true, and yet neither Alex
Karp nor anyone else at Palanteer has
ever been all that keen to shut the
rumor down. To this day, Carb likes to
use the fact that any involvement they
might have had would have been
classified to act coily whenever asked,
neither confirming nor denying. Did your
company helped to track and kill
uh Osama bin Laden?
You know, we can never I'll tell you the
only the closest thing to an answer like
is like there are when you when you look
at the like when you open the paper and
look in the news about these kind of
things, there's a
2/3 chance depending on the country
involved that somehow my company was
involved which is I mean we're you know
we're 4,000 people. We have just under
two billion in revenue. So it's it's you
know market cap goes up and down. It is
surprising the footprint that we have.
>> This rumor put Palunteer on the map. By
2013, it added contracts with the US
Department of Homeland Security, the
National Security Agency, the FBI, the
Centers for Disease Control, the Marine
Corps, the Air Force, and several other
arms of the US government. All of this
was made possible by some pretty
aggressive sales tactics. See, early on,
Alex Karp had made a big deal of the
fact that Palanteer didn't have a
dedicated sales team. He wanted to rely
on the strength of the product and
client recommendations. And yet, this
isn't entirely true. Part of the deal
with bringing in Palanteer to your
government agency or company is that
they'll also send to you what they call,
in a somewhat cringe attempt to sound
more military, a forward deployed
engineer. This is someone who is
embedded in your team to help tailor
Palanteer software to your needs.
They're mainly an engineer, but they're
also not not a saleserson. Commentators
have long described Palanteer as using a
land and expand strategy in which once
an organization hires them to work on
one project, they'll desperately try to
expand throughout your organization.
Hence how one contract with the NHS
quickly saw the company work its way
into seemingly every corner of the
British government. But more on that
later. If you don't let them keep
expanding, you'll soon feel their wrath.
When Palanteer was denied a contract
with the US Army, Palanteer sued them,
arguing that the Army's preference for
hiring a company to develop a bespoke
system was wasteful when they could just
buy in Palanteer Gotham instead.
Palanteer also wasn't quick to let go if
a customer decided that it had had
enough. In 2017, the New York Police
Department decided to end its contract
with Palanteer. It had decided the
software wasn't actually as good as it
had been built to be and had developed
an in-house alternative instead. As the
NYPD began to make the switch, however,
they found Palanteer reluctant to let
them have copies of any analysis which
had been produced using Palanteer Gotham
during the course of their contract.
They were allowed to have their own
data, of course. Remember, Palanteer is
not a data company. But any connections
or other discoveries the MIPD staff had
made during the contract was now
inaccessible. All of this is before we
get into the more obvious human rights
concerns which came with the expansion
of Palanteer's contract from military
uses into domestic policing. The
transition from predicting the locations
of IEDs in Afghanistan and hunting down
terrorists to catching criminals in New
York City or LA was easy from a
technical standpoint. Ethically, it was
far murkier. PayPal's eagle had often
been compared to minority report, but
Palanteer was quite literally offering
something akin to predictive policing,
in which the belief was that crunching
enough data could predict where, when,
and who was going to commit a crime
before they did. These controversies
would only increase, however, after the
US government suddenly found itself
under the command of Palanteer
co-founder Peter Teal's old friend,
Donald Trump.
I want to skip forward a bit here to
2026. In April of this year, someone at
Palanteer decided that it was prudent
for the company's official X account to
post a 22point manifesto explaining its
view on the world. It's hard to choose
which of the bullet points to pick out
because they were all pretty zesty.
There was the support for national
service, the terade against inclusivity,
the controversial thoughts on the quote
postwar neutering of Germany and Japan.
There were also two separate points
which were effectively about council
culture. None of these points, however,
were entirely new. The manifesto was
effectively a contents page and summary
of Alex Karp's 2025 book, The
Technological Republic. The
technological republic is in many ways a
kind of grabbag of ideas from around the
current domain of conservative thought.
See for example Karp's complaint about a
supposed intolerance of religious belief
among the American elite. And yet there
are a few ideas in there which are vital
for understanding both Karp as an
individual and Palanteer as a company.
For one, yes, Alex Karp has abandoned
pretty much all of his once deeply
cherished left-wing ideals. someone who
as recently as 2023 donated to the Joe
Biden and Kla Harris presidential
campaign has now well and truly joined
the ranks of the populist right. More
than this though, Alex Karp doesn't view
his political beliefs as in any way
separate from his running of the
company. Neither does he think they
should be. Karp is adamant that all
companies should be political, driven by
purpose, not just by making money.
Karp's book devotes significant page
space to raging against companies like
Google, Facebook, and other tech firms,
which he accuses of wasting employee
talents on trivialities,
advertising, food delivery, messaging
apps. Is this, he asks, the best that we
can expect from our tech sector?
Neither, Karp argues, is the
contemporary world particularly lacking
in big challenges that the tech industry
could be tackling. Most notably, he
argues war. See, Alex Karp's worldview
today is every bit as cynical as Peter
Teal's. Conflict is everywhere, and
anyone who denies that is simply naive.
There's a reason that Palanteer's
military and policing product is called
Gotham. This is a company which views
the whole world as a kind of
crimeinfested Gotham city, ready to
erupt at any given moment unless someone
forces some order onto it. Karp argues
that even in recent decades when many
people in wealthy nations have felt that
they are living through times of peace,
that peace has only been made possible
through the unmatched might of the US
armed forces keeping threats at bay.
When Karp says that his company's
mission is to defend the West, he's not
just using the West as a shorthand for a
group of rich countries. He is a
fundamental believer in the West as a
civilization, as perhaps the
civilization. from Greece to Rome to
Britain to the United States of America.
Karp argues that tech companies are some
of the best resourced and highest
profile companies in the contemporary
world should be serving the interests of
that civilization in particular in its
manifestation as the American state. He
targets particular contempt at Google
which following an employee revolt in
2018 chose not to renew a contract with
the Pentagon which saw them working on
the AI drone targeting system project
Maven. Carp shouldn't complain too much.
Palanteer ended up picking up that
contract. It was Project Maven which was
reportedly used to choose targets during
the US's strikes on Iran in 2026.
Nevertheless, KB saw the refusal of
employees at Google, Microsoft, and
elsewhere to work on military projects
as borderline treasonous. The
Technological Republic opens with a kind
of cliche quote from Michael Sandal.
>> Fundamentalists rush in where liberals
fear to tread. Palanteer employees often
frame any ethically questionable
activities which their technologies
enable as necessary in order to stave
off some often unspecified greater
threat. And yet Palanter's commitment to
defending the West is so all-consuming,
so fundamentalist itself that there are
precious few liberties the company has
been willing to trample on in order to
fulfill it. In 2014, Palanteer signed a
$42 million deal with the United States
Immigration and Customs Enforcement to
develop a new case management system.
ICE, of course, was about to become big
news. The agency had been in the
business of deporting people since 2003,
but the election of Donald Trump saw it
drowning in both resources and
prominence. Palanteer would be central
to all of this. The company has built
several tools for ICE, each of which
allows the agency to pull information to
better help it identify, track, and
detain suspected illegal migrants. At
time of recording, the company is
working on a software package called
Immigration OS, which will collect both
public and privately held data to this
end. In terms of military business,
Palante's apparent success at locating
Osama bin Laden and later identifying
potential locations of IEDs in
Afghanistan has since developed into
systems for targeting drone and missile
strikes. This includes aiding Israel's
genocide in Gaza. Alex Karpas himself
admitted to being involved in the
killing of Palestinians. So the primary
source of of death in Palestine is the
fact that Hamas has realized that there
are millions and millions of useful
idiots that will
>> using that excuse. This is why you don't
GET A FLASH. DARE YOU. YOUR AI AND YOUR
TECHNOLOGY FROM PALANTEER KILLS
PALESTINIANS.
>> Mostly terrorists. That's true. KP has
also boasted that Palant's products have
been in great demand by the Israeli
Defense Ministry during the genocide
with reports suggesting that the company
has been providing the IDF with its
artificial intelligence platform which
uses AI to select and prioritize
targets. That same technology appears to
have been used heavily by both
belligerents during the United States
and Israel strikes on Iran in early
2026. And yet, Palanteer isn't just a
military contractor. While the company
has come under plenty of criticism for
its participation in brutal deportations
and automated genocide, the real threat
to its business has come from trying to
continue those operations whilst also
trying to solicit more domestic
operations and contracts too.
>> I think we're living through two big
global changes. One is geopolitical and
the other is technology. The interesting
thing is they're happening at once. This
is Louis Mosley, CEO of Palunteer UK.
The first thing which always has to be
said about Louis Mosley is that if that
last name rings a bell, then yes, he is
the grandson of Oswald Mosley and Diana
Mittford, the leader of the British
Union fascists and his Hitleradoring
wife were married in Joseph Gerbal's
house in Berlin with Hitler present as
guest of honor. Louisie Mosley is keen
to distance himself from his
grandparents. And yet, neither is he an
apolitical figure in the way that he
would sometimes like to be seen. He was
previously heavily involved in the
Conservative Party and in 2023 gave an
address to the Alliance for Responsible
Citizenship Conference, organized by the
owners of GB News and headlined by
Jordan Peterson. The speech was a
clichéed collage of Petersonenstyle
grievances about how the poor afflicted
attendees of this 1,500 pound ahead
conference were actually the victims of
horrific censorship.
>> Those who challenged the official
narrative on, for example, the origins
of the COVID pandemic or mass migration
have felt the weight of this whole of
society effort firsthand.
>> Louis Mosley's connection to his
grandfather has not been a barrier to
his advancement at Palanteer. When
Louisie first met with Alex Karp for his
job interview, Karp chose to recite at
length a speech which Oswald Mosley had
given in 1939 at a rally against the UK
going to war with Nazi Germany. Karp
reportedly then did some Tai Chi moves,
then swiftly awarded Mosley the job.
Being the head of Palunteer in the UK
might sound pretty small Fry, or perhaps
there's a risk of it coming across as if
I'm just interested in Palanteer in the
UK because I happen to live here. The
UK, however, is by far the company's
biggest outpost outside of the US.
>> That's a very little known fact about
Palanteer is you you you could in lots
of ways stick a made in Britain sticker
on on the product, right? Like it's it's
made in London.
>> Palanteer has had a presence in the UK
since the late 2000s when GCHQ, which is
the UK's equivalent to the NSA, was so
impressed by Palanteer Gotham that it
scrapped plans to build its own software
suite in favor of buying in Gotham
instead. This was in spite of concerns
about becoming reliant on a product
which was both outside of GCHQ and
external to the UK. Palanteer's big
break, however, came in 2019. That
August, Peter Teal held a meeting with
the then Prime Minister Boris Johnson
and his adviser Dominic Cummings in
Downing Street. The meeting was recorded
as private and remained completely
secret until the leak of the so-called
Boris files in 2025. A year later, with
the CO9 pandemic in full swing,
Palanteer was awarded a so-called
emergency contract to provide data
services to help the NHS and the
government monitor how the disease was
spreading as well as to keep track of
things like bed capacity. What was
interesting about this particular deal
is that while Palanteer is generally
considered a pretty expensive company to
do business with, they agreed to do this
work with the NHS for just £1. Following
the company's land and expand strategy,
Palanteer would soon spin that contract
up into a further set of deals which it
won uncontested. These came in at 60
million. The even bigger deal, however,
would come in 2023 when against
opposition from the British Medical
Association. Palanteer was awarded a£330
million contract to supply the NHS with
its commercial platform Foundry as part
of the NHS's efforts to improve its use
of data. But in order to talk properly
about that, I guess we ought to first
explain Foundry.
Early on, it became pretty clear that
Palanteer was always going to be limited
if it could only rely on military
contracts. There are only so many
militaries in the world, after all, and
even fewer if your whole thing is
defending the West. As early as the late
2000s, then Palanteer began trying to
develop software that they could sell to
businesses. Their first attempt was
Palanteer Finance or what was later
renamed Palanteer Metropolis. Metropolis
was designed for investors and traders,
but on its surface, it performed much
the same task as Gotham. It was a
quantitative analysis tool which aimed
to take the huge amount of data which
investment firms have at their disposal
and make it more easily available and
readable to analysts. Palanteer
Metropolis didn't have a bad start. The
company struck up a partnership with
Thompson Reuters to work together on the
project and pitch it to relevant
institutions. They even managed to land
a high-profile client in the form of JP
Morgan. The challenge was that
Metropolis wasn't just a quantitative
analysis tool. It was designed to be a
complete operating system for the
financial services industry, which was
to have consequences. See, behind the
scenes, Metropolis also worked to
monitor JP Morgan employees to ensure
that they weren't stealing or up to
anything else illegal, which isn't
unusual. Defending against so-called
insider threats is a standard practice
within financial services companies. The
problem came when the head of this
division and ex secret service agent
allegedly got a bit too interested in
what his colleagues were up to. Working
with a team of more than a hundred
forward deployed engineers from
Palanteer, the security chief became
obsessed, listening into calls, reading
emails, and combing through browsing
histories of employees like a one-man
star. Palanteer Metropolis never really
caught on. Financial services firms just
turned out to be a bit too stuck in
their ways. And yet, Palanteer was
desperate to find a route into
commercial rather than just government
work. They would find that route in with
Palanteer Foundry. Palanteer pitches
Foundry as a complete operating system
for the modern corporation. The idea is
that it can give you a complete overview
of your business at any given time.
Palanteer are keen on the idea of the
digital twin. Their software allows you
to create a digital representation of
every part of your organization. every
office, factory and vehicle, every
customer, client and supplier, every
product and service you offer, every
order, every process, every
relationship. The result in theory is
complete oversight of your company and
everything it does. Where Metropolis
faltered, Foundry has thrived. Airbus,
Walmart, Nokia, 3M, the command strip
people, Chipotle, and hundreds of other
companies all use Foundry to keep track
of what's going on in their companies.
When Palanteer was awarded its 330
million pound deal with the NHS in 2023,
the deal was to implement a customized
version of Foundry for the Health
Service. Data management is something
the NHS had been trying to solve for
some time. See, beyond the issue of
public or private, one of the benefits
of the NHS is that it's all one system.
Most Brits get most of their health care
through the service, which should come
with all kinds of potential benefits in
terms of consistency of care and
management of resources. In practice
though, provision is split between a
whole bunch of different hospital
trusts, doctor's surgeries, and other
care providers, many of which have
different systems for maintaining
patient records, keeping track of
supplies and capacity, which is a real
lost opportunity. Bringing things
together in one system would make it so
much easier for clinicians to be able to
access comprehensive records for
patients, for managers to see where
there are bottlenecks in capacity, and
even for researchers to be able to study
and predict disease outbreaks and other
health issues. In 2023, the NHS thus ran
a tender process to find a company to
develop what it was calling the
federated data platform. In truth,
though, Palunteer had a clear advantage
in the bidding process. The pre-existing
relationship they built up with the
organization during the emergency COVID
contract and subsequent uncontested
contract meant it was clearly the easier
path for the NHS to just stick with
Palanteer going forward. There were
voices of dissent about this secretive
contrarian tech company being handed
access to the healthcare data of an
entire nation from the very start.
Campaigners criticized the heavily
redacted version of Palant's contract
which was made available to the public.
Doctors themselves raised deep concerns
about the health service working with a
military corporation which had been
heavily involved in Israel's genocide in
Gaza. Over the past 6 months, however,
opposition to Palunteer's involvement in
the NHS and the many, many, many other
contracts it has signed with many, many,
many other parts of the UK government
has snowballed. MPs have been pushing
for the government to kick the company
out of the UK's public services
entirely. Palanteer lost a contract
matching refugees from Ukraine with host
families in the UK. The mayor of London
blocked a contract between Palanteer and
the Metropolitan Police. So too, if
Palanteer recently lost contract in
France and in Germany, things are
suddenly not looking so good for
Palanteer outside of the US. In order to
understand why, we need to look at one
more idea, one which is far simpler than
either of the others that we've looked
at in this video, and that's trust.
on the data trust issue. We have no
interest in patient data in the UK. It's
not our business model. It's not the
legal basis on which we operate in the
same way that Microsoft Excel or
Microsoft Word or email is used in the
NHS. And again, that is NHS data.
Microsoft doesn't have access to it, nor
do we to NHS data. So, I can really
reassure you and viewers that that's the
case. This is Louis Mosley speaking
during what currently feels like an
endless and ongoing press store. Here in
the UK, Mosley has effectively become
the company's chief flack jacket,
fighting off the barrage of criticism
currently being thrown at the company.
All of this matters. Palanter's contract
to develop the NHS's federated data
platform comes with a break clause which
the government can trigger should it
wish in February 2027. There is
currently a lot of pressure on the NHS
and the government to use that clause
and maybe even to rethink the many,
many, many other deals that the UK
government has with Palanteer, which
means that poor Louie has been fighting
for his life. One of his favorite
talking points is that Palanter's
critics are ideologically motivated.
It's not that they don't think
Palanteer's software is good enough.
It's not that they're arguing that it's
too expensive. Not first and foremost,
anyway. For the most part, Louie claims
Palanteer's critics just don't like
Peter Teal, don't like Alex Carb, and
don't like the company's connections to
the Trump administration and its actions
in Gaza. That he's repeated it so much
clearly means that he thinks this is a
good argument. He's also in many ways
right. And yet, it's not exactly the
Trump card he thinks it is. Throughout
the time I was researching this company
and particularly its contracts here in
the UK, there's been one key idea which
has come up time and time again. Trust.
Data platforms like Palanteers are only
as good as the data which goes into
them. When the US struck a school in
Iran in early 2026, it was reported that
Palanteer's Maven smart system may have
been involved in choosing the school as
a target. That recommendation appeared
to be the result of the system being fed
with outdated information. If people
don't trust a system, they are more
likely to feed it with false
information. This is precisely what
happened when employees at JP Morgan
suspected their head of insider threats
might have been spying on them. In a
hospital setting, the consequences of
this are far greater. If a patient is
concerned that any information they
reveal to their doctor is at risk of
being accessed by the police, their
employer, immigration enforcement, the
tax man, the intelligence services, or
anyone else they might not want to see
it. They might either give a doctor
false information or worse just not go
to the doctor at all. Palanteer
continues to protest that they are not a
data company and that two organizations
using their software does not mean that
both those organizations have access to
each other's data. In the end though,
whether they actually do or not doesn't
really matter. The fact that Palanteer
has gained this reputation as a big
personal data hoover and a pretty shady
one at that means that it is still going
to affect the ability of doctors,
nurses, and other health care
professionals to provide their patients
with good healthcare. In the era of
international tensions we find ourselves
in, however, even the basic geography of
these deals can place trust in question,
too. In June 2026, the AI company
Anthropic announced that it was having
to abruptly disable aspects of its AI
chatbot clawed under order from the
Trump administration. The model was
deemed to be so powerful by the US
government that they decided to ban all
foreign nationals from using it. This
new protectionism has also raised
questions of trust for international
users of Palanteer. Organizations like
the French internal intelligence
services have opted to break ties with
Palanteer precisely because they feel
that being reliant on a foreignade tool
presents a clear vulnerability. The fact
that Alex K, Peter Teal and other
members of Palanteer's seauite have been
so clear about the fact that their
company exists to defend American
interests is also likely to continue to
raise questions about whether any
government organization outside of the
US should trust this company with their
information. But all of the blame for
the fog of distrust which surrounds
Palanteer can be placed directly at the
feet of Alex Karp and Peter Te. If
criticism of Palanteer feels
ideological, it is in large part because
they have chosen to flaunt their beliefs
so loudly. These are people who have
been desperate to tell the world about
their wacky right-wing ideas. They have
thrown themselves at every opportunity
to participate in death and destruction.
They have actively sought out
opportunities to erode human rights. If
that makes criticism of the company
ideological, then it is because this is
a uniquely ideological company. And many
people see that ideology as horrific.
And people are allowed to not like you
for that reason.
Palanteer's various controversies are
sure to be ongoing news stories for
quite some time. It's the kind of thing
which we're likely to be covering a lot
on my still relatively new show, Slow
News Day. Slow Newsuesday is a very
nearly daily news show in which my team
and I provide in-depth explainers on the
week's biggest politics and news
stories. stuff like Talented, stuff like
the Iran War, stuff like the current
turmoil at the top of British politics.
Well, maybe that's uh all sorted itself
out between us uh filming this and again
now. Maybe we release two episodes of
Slow Newsuesday every week here on
YouTube or wherever you get your
podcasts, but we release two extra
episodes exclusively on Nebula. You've
probably heard of Nebula by now. It's a
premium streaming service launched by
myself and a bunch of other Inquisitive
creators. creators like Legal Eagle,
TLDDR News, and Man Carrying Thing. It
allows you to watch all of our normal
videos, ad and sponsor free, but also
gets you access to a whole treasure
trove of exclusive shows and films, too.
That includes two extra episodes of slow
news day a week, but it also includes my
featurelength Nebula original film,
Boomers. It includes exclusive stuff
from Lindsay Ellis. You also get early
access to videos from Tom Scott and
Patrick H. Williams. Better still, if
you sign up to Nebula using my link
go.nebula.tv/topnicholas,
you can get 50% off an annual plan. This
brings your monthly subscription down to
just £250 a month or whatever the
equivalent is where you are. It really
is a great deal for such a fantastic
catalog of exclusive shows. That link
again is go.nebula.tv/tomnicholas.
Thank you so so much for watching once
again and I'll see you over on Nebula.
All that's left for me to do is to say a
massive thank you to the people who
support my work over on Patreon. Those
people are Richard Gary Dickon Spain,
Bill Mitchell, ZedC Reese, Zoe Alden,
Alexander Blank, Neil Bildgard, Sophia
R, Sergio Suarez, Richard Rapun, Gabriel
Ko, Jimmy Dunn, Fiasco Linguini, Agent
Maxwell, The Third Workshop, Emil
Jarabar, Yillimson, Paulus Edus, Sam
Portonato, and not Medi. If you'd like
to join them in supporting uh what we do
here, then you can find out all about
how to do that over at
patreon.com/tomicholas.